{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In this city, Ezra Pound and Igor Stravinsky are buried on the island of San Michele. Operation Bowler targeted this city’s harbor with a precision air strike. One traveler from this city was imprisoned in Genoa, where Rustichello da Pisa recorded his stories in Il Milione. The admirer of the Polish boy Tadzio, Gustav von Aschenbach, dies in this city in a 1912 novella by Thomas Mann. Marco Polo was from, for ten points, what Italian city, famous for its canals?",
      "answer": "Venice"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sigmund Rascher’s experiments were used to test technology for this military force. Members of this group carried out the Stalag Luft III murders after a group of Allied POWs escaped from one of their prisons. Its leader committed suicide after being sentenced to death during the Nuremberg Trials. The Junkers [yoon-kers] Ju-87 was heavily used by this organization for dive-bombing. Herman Goering led, for ten points, what branch of the Nazi military that bombed Britain?",
      "answer": [
        "Luftwaffe",
        "the Nazi German Air Force"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This individual earned a “production E” in a song by Redd Evans and John Jacob Loeb. This figure inspired a National Historical Park in Richmond, California that is home to the SS Red Oak Victory. Geraldine Doyle was the inspiration for one depiction of this character by Westinghouse employee J. Howard Miller, which depicts her with a red bandana and flexed bicep, saying “We Can Do It!” for ten points, name this icon that encouraged American women to take factory jobs during World War II.",
      "answer": "Rosie the Riveter"
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1864 conference in this city created 72 proposed resolutions that formed its country’s first constitution; that conference followed one in Charlottetown. The former Iroquois village of Stadacona is in this modern city, which was founded by Samuel de Champlain in 1608. The Battle of the Plains of Abraham was fought in what is now, for ten points, what namesake capital city of a French-speaking Canadian province?",
      "answer": "Quebec City"
    },
    {
      "question": "Shortly after performing this action, one athlete, born Chris Jackson, was suspended by the NBA after refusing to stand for “The Star-Spangled Banner.” The New York State Athletic Commission suspended one athlete for draft evasion, which that athlete justified on grounds of having performed this action. A Milwaukee Buck and future Laker changed his name from Lew Alcindor several years after performing this action, which includes reciting the shahada. For ten points, name this religious action performed by star athletes Kareem Abdul-Jabbar and Muhammad Ali.",
      "answer": [
        "converting to Islam or becomeing a Muslim",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Russian Empire used Agvan Dorzhiev as a contact to one of these people. One of these people fled in response to a military expedition led by Francis Younghusband, and his successor called for a democratic “zone of peace” in his Strasbourg proposal. These people are said to be reincarnations of Avalokitesvara, and the most recent of these people went to exile in India after a 1959 uprising was crushed by Chinese forces. For ten points, name this position currently held by Tenzin Gyatso, the leader of Tibetan Buddhism.",
      "answer": "Dalai Lamas"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man added an Andante spinanto to the beginning of one of his compositions. The third movement of his B-flat minor second piano sonata is a funeral march. The revolutions of 1848 inspired this composer’s lover George Sand to nickname one of his works “Heroic,” and he was inspired by a dog chasing its tail to write a piece that is actually ninety seconds long. For ten points, what piano virtuoso wrote the Minute Waltz and several polonaises inspired by his native Poland?",
      "answer": "Fr´ed´eric Franc¸ois Chopin or Fryderyk Franciszek Chopin"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to its invocation, this ruling was “sincerely believed to be an act of justice warranted by the Constitution.” This ruling came with one hundred days’ notice and specifically exempted New Orleans and the land that was to become West Virginia. The victory at Antietam led to its issuing, which only immediately took effect in territory controlled by Union forces. For ten points, name this executive order issued on January 1, 1863 by President Lincoln, which freed over three million slaves in the South.",
      "answer": "Emancipation Proclamation"
    },
    {
      "question": "One protest in this country used the slogans “Be Realists: Demand the Impossible!” and “Alcohol Kills; Take LSD” and was led by Daniel Cohn-Bendit. This country’s riot police, the CRS, violently put down that protest, which had been removed from an administrative building at Nanterre. Georges Pompidou was initially unable to control May 1968 riots at the Sorbonne in, for ten points, what country, that reacted two months later by re-electing Charles de Gaulle?",
      "answer": "France"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man appointed Edward Douglass White as Chief Justice. He used the “Saxbe fix” to appoint Philander Knox, who carried out a program of promoting corporate interests in foreign countries, or “dollar diplomacy.” In his re-election campaign, he only won Utah and Vermont, partially because his predecessor split from the Republican Party to run on the Bull Moose ticket. For ten points, name this President who succeeded Theodore Roosevelt, then served as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court.",
      "answer": "William Howard Taft"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Charles Kinsey, John Ames, and Thomas Gilpin created early American machines for continuous production of this good. Bryan Donkin built a prototype of the Fourdrinier machine, which creates this good via a “form, press, dry” method. A high lignin content in the pulp will weaken this good, so the kraft process is used to separate out the needed cellulose. The Han dynasty invented, for ten points, what material that replaced silk and parchment as a medium for writing?",
        "answer": "paper"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This material was used for writing, as well as rope and baskets, prior to the invention of paper. The Egyptian Book of the Dead was preserved on this material, as was a mathematical text named for Alexander Rhind.",
        "answer": [
          "papyrus",
          "Rhind papyrus"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Pirates attacked this river’s traffic from Cave-in-Rock. The first European to chart this river was Robert de la Salle. Its largest city was built along a namesake Falls, and a French building at this river’s fork was burned in the Battle of Fort Duquesne. It was known to people traveling the Underground Railroad as the “River Jordan,” as it was the border between free and slave states. For ten points, name this river that flows past Louisville and Cincinnati.",
        "answer": "Ohio River"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Allegheny and Monongahela Rivers meet to form the Ohio in what present-day city, the site of Fort Duquesne?",
        "answer": "Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The non-Quaker Society of Friends led an independence movement in this nation during the early 19th century. One of this country’s islands, known for its production of mastic, or chewing gum, was the site of a massacre depicted in a Eugene Delacroix [de-la-quah] painting. Lord Byron died in the siege of Missolonghi during this nation’s war for independence, led by Alexander Ypsilantis against the Ottomans. For ten points, name this Balkan nation, the birthplace of Western democracy, where Ottoman forces stored munitions in the Parthenon.",
        "answer": "Greece"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Delacroix’s painting depicts the desolation after the Massacre at this Greek island.",
        "answer": "Chios"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Akrotiri was destroyed by one of these events near what is now Cape Kolumbo. The ROTAS-SATOR and ROMA-MILO magic squares were discovered in the ruins of another of these events, from which Rectina was to be rescued from Stabiae by a fast ship commanded by Pliny the Elder. For ten points, name these devastating events that took place on Santorini circa 1500 BC, wiping out the Minoans, and on Vesuvius in 79 AD, destroying the town of Pompeii.",
        "answer": [
          "volcanic eruptions",
          "descriptions of volcanoes"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A pyroclastic flow from Vesuvius destroyed this town southwest of the volcano, as opposed to Pompeii and Oplontis to the south and east. Its high standard of living is evident through the marble ruins it left behind.",
        "answer": "Herculaneum"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An expedition to this site was piloted by Simon Fernandez and was undertaken to fulfill a charter granted to Sir Walter Raleigh. John White instructed residents of this settlement to use the Maltese Cross as a symbol of distress. Located off the coast of North Carolina, a 1590 expedition that visited this site found the word “CROATOAN” carved into a post, but no residents. For ten points, name this first English attempt to permanently settle New World, known as the “Lost Colony.”",
        "answer": "Roanoke Colony"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What girl, born on Roanoke Island in 1587, was the first English child born in the New World?",
        "answer": "Virginia Dare"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While awaiting trial for his role with the Chicago Eight, Abbie Hoffman wrote about this event, including his fight with Pete Townshend. During this event, Chip Monck announced “It is suggested that you stay away from [the brown acid].” Travel mishaps prevented Iron Butterfly from attending this event, which was held at Max Yasgur’s farm, and included performances by Jefferson Airplane and The Who. Over 400,000 people attended, for ten points, what 1969 music festival in New York?",
        "answer": "Woodstock Music Festival or Woodstock Music & Art Fair"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This guitarist, who died at age 27, used heavy distortion and feedback in a legendary rendition of the Star-Spangled Banner at Woodstock.",
        "answer": "Jimi Hendrix"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist invented the parallel linkage, found in some automobile axles. This scientist, along with his business partners Matthew Boulton and James Keir, developed a machine to copy ink documents. This scientist’s separation of the condenser and cylinder in a previous invention developed by Thomas Newcomen allowed it to become the most widely used power source during the Industrial Revolution. For ten points, name this inventor of a rotary steam engine and the namesake of the SI unit for power.",
        "answer": "James Watt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "James Watt coined this unit of measure, equal to about 750 Watts, as a relation to the power output of manually spinning mill wheels.",
        "answer": "horsepower"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this battle, James Calhoun’s men held high ground but lost their horses when their handlers were shot. Reports of incoming soldiers shortly before this battle were dismissed by the elder Runs the Enemy, who noted that Americans never attacked in midday. The death of the scout Bloody Knife triggered Marcus Reno’s retreat from this battle, shortly before the 7th Cavalry was utterly destroyed. For ten points, name this June 1876 battle in which George Custer made his failed “last stand.”",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Little Bighorn or Battle of the Greasy Grass",
          "Custer’s Last Stand before Custer is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the battle, this Lakota warrior led a charge to break the American lines. A memorial to this man is being carved in the Black Hills roughly 20 miles from Mount Rushmore.",
        "answer": "Crazy Horse or Thasunke Witko"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Watergate",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. President who resigned after the Watergate scandal.",
          "answer": "Richard Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who claimed “our long national nightmare is over” after succeeding Nixon as President.",
          "answer": "Gerald Ford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Newspaper for which Woodward and Bernstein investigated the story.",
          "answer": "Washington Post"
        },
        {
          "question": "Codenamed source, a former CIA admin, that provided Woodward and Bernstein with important leaks.",
          "answer": [
            "Deep Throat",
            "W. Mark Felt"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Fundraising organization led by John Mitchell that funded that Watergate burglars’ defense fund.",
          "answer": "Committee for the Re-Election of the President"
        },
        {
          "question": "1973 event in which the Attorney General and Deputy Attorney General resigned, rather than fire Special Prosecutor Archibald Cox.",
          "answer": "Saturday Night Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "British journalist who paid hundreds of thousands of dollars to interview the resigned President in 1977.",
          "answer": "David Frost"
        },
        {
          "question": "White House Chief of Staff who assisted in the cover-up and resigned in April 1973.",
          "answer": [
            "Harry Robbins “Bob”",
            "H.R. Haldeman"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Winston Churchill",
      "prompt": "Concerning Winston Churchill’s career, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Political position he held during World War II and the 1950s as head of government of the United Kingdom.",
          "answer": "Prime Minister"
        },
        {
          "question": "Branch of the British armed forces that he praised for their performance against the Luftwaffe.",
          "answer": "Royal Air Force or RAF"
        },
        {
          "question": "1938 agreement, signed by Neville Chamberlain and Adolf Hitler, that he vocally opposed.",
          "answer": "Munich Agreement"
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed World War I campaign he organized as First Lord of the Admiralty, in which over 8,000 Australians died.",
          "answer": "Gallipoli campaign"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian World War II battle, declared by Churchill to be “perhaps, the end of the beginning.”",
          "answer": "Second Battle of El Alamein"
        },
        {
          "question": "Labour Party leader who defeated him in 1945 and 1950 elections.",
          "answer": "Clement Attlee"
        },
        {
          "question": "War in which he was captured and held as a POW.",
          "answer": "Second Boer War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deputy and Foreign Secretary who succeeded him in 1955, leading Britain during the Suez Crisis.",
          "answer": "Sir Anthony Eden"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Enemies of Rome",
      "prompt": "Which person or group...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Led a Carthaginian army, including elephants, over the Alps during the Second Punic War?",
          "answer": "Hannibal Barca"
        },
        {
          "question": "Did not sack Rome when Pope Leo I convinced Attila to turn this group back?",
          "answer": "Huns"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a gladiator and slave revolt leader, whose followers were crucified along the Appian Way?",
          "answer": "Spartacus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were led by Vercingetorix but was defeated by Julius Caesar at Alesia in modern France?",
          "answer": "Gauls"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sacked Rome in 410 AD under their leader, Alaric?",
          "answer": "Visigoths"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led the Iceni against Suetonius in Britannia before her AD 60 death?",
          "answer": "Boudica or Boadicea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proclaimed “Woe to the vanquished” when he sacked Rome in 390 BC?",
          "answer": "Brennus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ambushed Quinctillius Varus and his former Roman allies in Teutoberg Forest, causing Augustus to shout “Give me back my legions!”",
          "answer": "Arminius or Hermann"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A call for the devolution of this region was suggested by the Kilbrandon Report and was opposed by Neil Kinnock in 1979. The Marcher Lords governed this nation’s eastern border. In the early 1400’s, Henry V subdued Owen (20 pts)",
        "Glendower, a rebel from this nation. The titled ruler of this nation wears a badge with three white feathers, and a red (10 pts)",
        "dragon appears on this nation’s flag over a white and green background. Llewellyn the Great once led, for ten points, what constituent country of the UK whose capital is Cardiff?"
      ],
      "answer": "Wales"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Hans Oster plotted a coup d’´etat if war with this country broke out. Political dissidents in this country met at the Magic Lantern theater, forming the Civic Forum. Charter 77 was signed by dissidents in this country, including (20 pts)",
        "Jan Patoˇcka [pa-totch-ka]. Gustav Husak led a period of normalization in this country, which underwent the (10 pts)",
        "Velvet Divorce under its last president, Vaclav Havel. For ten points, name this country that dissolved in 1993 into modern day components whose capitals are Bratislava and Prague."
      ],
      "answer": "Czechoslovakia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Vela Incident was likely a result of one of these programs. One of these programs was exposed by The Sunday Times with the testimony of Mordechai Vanunu. South Africa was the first country to (20 pts)",
        "voluntarily end one of these programs. Another of these programs carried out Operation Smiling Buddha, under the watch of Indira Gandhi. India, (10 pts)",
        "Pakistan, and Israel have refused to sign a treaty banning the proliferation of these programs. For ten points, name this type of military program, one of which claimed success in North Korea in January 2016."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "programs for the development of nuclear weapons",
        "any equivalent for nuclear weapons, including hydrogen bomb before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Navigation Acts supported this policy, for which Jean-Baptiste Colbert advocated as Louis XIV’s Finance Minister. This practice’s emphasis on (20 pts)",
        "trade balance contrasts with the Physiocratic view that labor created national wealth. Colonial expansion and high (10 pts)",
        "tariffs were trademarks of, for ten points, what economic practice in which countries manipulated their economies to gain more monetary wealth than rival nations, which dominated Europe in the 17th and 18th centuries?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "mercantilism",
        "bullionism"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist used his son, Jarvis, as a model for Michael Schwerner in one work. Another work by this artist shows four U.S. Marshalls escorting six-year-old Ruby Bridges to an all-white school. This man’s work for LOOK magazine include Southern Justice and The (20 pts)",
        "Problem We All Live With, and he depicted a man dissenting at a town meeting and an old woman serving a turkey as part of a series inspired by (10 pts)",
        "FDR’s 1941 State of the Union. For ten points, name this artist who illustrated the Four Freedoms series and many covers for the Saturday Evening Post."
      ],
      "answer": "Norman Rockwell"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One artist from this country depicted a Nativity-like vaccination scene and images of poison gas manufacturing in a series of 27 works. Another work by that artist from this country was ordered destroyed by (20 pts)",
        "Nelson Rockefeller. Another artist from this country painted a double self-portrait whose figures are connected by an artery; that artist married the creator of (10 pts)",
        "Detroit Industry and a controversial work depicting Lenin, Man at the Crossroads. For ten points, name this home country of Frida Kahlo and muralist Diego Rivera."
      ],
      "answer": "Mexico"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The deciding vote for this amendment was cast by Harry Burn, a Tennessee legislator who was persuaded to “put the rat in ratification.” This amendment overruled Minor v. Happersett, and its ratification was upheld in (20 pts)",
        "Leser v. Garnett. This amendment was advocated for by the Silent Sentinels and a 1913 parade organized by (10 pts)",
        "Alice Paul, and was popularly named after one of its first proponents, Susan B. Anthony. For ten points, name this 1920 Constitutional amendment that granted women the right to vote."
      ],
      "answer": "19th Amendment"
    }
  ]
}